So, let's try then to modify our
solution so that we can avoid deadlocks.
As we discussed before, as long as we make
sure one of the following things cannot happen:
hold and wait, no preemption or
circular wait (I am of course
excluding mutual exclusion!) then we are done.
Can we prevent circular wait from happening?
This is not difficult, let's look at a
solution we call the request-resource-in-order.
The idea is simple, we only change the code
executed by the last philosopher, so that he/she
tries to take the right chopstick first
and the left chopstick after that.
Let's argument why we cannot have
a circular wait in this case.
I am for simplicity assuming we only have
2 philosophers here, but you can extend
this reasoning to 3 or more philosophers.
Philosopher 0 takes chopstick 0 and then 1,
Philosopher 1 takes chopstick 0 and then 1.
Let's say Philosopher 0 waits for chopstick 0,
because philosopher 1 has it. If
philosopher 1 has chopstick 0 and
Philosopher 0 also waits for chopstick 0, then
Philosopher 1 can get chopstick 1 and eat.
Let's say Philosopher 1 waits for chopstick 1,
then it managed to get chopstick 0. But if it
has chopstick 0 then philosopher 1 cannot have
chopstick 1, which means philosopher 1 can eat.
Once we have proven this solution
cannot lead to a deadlock,
the next step is to reason about fairness.
Here, it is probably easy to see that the
solution might lead to the same philosopher
being the one that manages to get both
chopsticks over and over... (as before,
try to reason formally about this!).
A solution to this problem could be given by
having the semaphores implementing some fairness
mechanism, delivering the
signals to both philosophers.